<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.samaneskandarzadeh.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.samaneskandarzadeh.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-07-24T13:02:06+00:00</updated><id>https://www.samaneskandarzadeh.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Saman Eskandarzadeh</title><subtitle>Saman Eskandarzadeh Personal Website.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Pooled testing to help Australia tackle the second wave of COVID-19</title><link href="https://www.samaneskandarzadeh.com/blog/2020/pooledtesting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pooled testing to help Australia tackle the second wave of COVID-19" /><published>2020-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.samaneskandarzadeh.com/blog/2020/pooledtesting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.samaneskandarzadeh.com/blog/2020/pooledtesting/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Note:</strong>
A thought piece also featured in <a href="https://www.sydney.edu.au/content/dam/corporate/documents/business-school/research/itls/_thinking-series_2020-pieces_final-2021-01-21.pdf#page=35">Thinking Outside the Box Thought Pieces Series 2020</a>. 
The ideas and suggestions in this thought piece received good media attention and interest (e.g., <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2020-11-01/coronavirus-tests-in-australia-rise-could-pool-testing-help/12806524">ABC News</a>, <a href="https://www1.racgp.org.au/newsgp/clinical/covid-trade-offs-how-to-keep-testing-rates-high">newsGP</a>)</p>

<hr />
<div class="row">
        <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/novel pooled_h.jpg" data-zoomable="" />
</div>
<div class="caption">
    Credit: PAHO/WHO
</div>

<p>The threat of a second wave of COVID-19 looms on the horizon, with case numbers jumping in
Victoria since the Australian Government’s easing of restrictions. Prime Minister Scott Morrison
says outbreaks should be anticipated and that the government plans for localised restrictions to
contain the spread of the virus. “Pooled testing” is a cost-effective method for keeping track of
the virus by screening targeted/local populations for the virus – shows research at Sydney
University.</p>

<p>Prompt detection of the Sars-COV-2 virus is vital to the government’s approach to track and
contain the COVID-19 outbreak. Currently, testing occurs only in symptomatic individuals or close
contacts of those with confirmed disease. But an infected individual can be shedding virus for
days prior the development of any symptoms  <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/69/wr/mm6914e1.htm">[1]</a>, and some may not get any symptoms at all <a href="https://www.acpjournals.org/doi/10.7326/M20-3012">[2]</a>.</p>

<p>Extensive testing of the local population within a “hotspot” can ensure that infected people are
identified and quarantined before they infect others. However, it is also beyond Australia’s
budget and testing capacity to perform so many tests. A solution to this problem is pooled testing.
Pooled testing, as the name suggests, is the pooling together of a group of samples to run
only one test <a href="https://healthpolicy.usc.edu/research/getting-americans-back-to-work-and-school-with-pooled-testing">[3]</a>. For example, every week all households in one street could collect their own
samples of saliva <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/health/2020-07-01/new-saliva-test-for-covid-19-how-accurate-is-it/12406912">[4]</a>, mail those samples to a testing centre or deposit them in a testing bin
(methods already in use for screening programs such as Bowel Cancer screening). The lab then
combines together all the saliva samples from one household, or one street, or even one suburb,
into a single sample for testing. In this way the number of tests required can be reduced by a
factor of 10 or more.</p>

<p>Pooled testing makes sense where the disease prevalence (number of cases in a population at
a given time) is low. If the disease prevalence is high, then most of the grouped samples will be
positive, which then requires individual testing of all the individuals in that group – rendering
pooled testing a useless exercise to reduce test numbers.</p>

<p>Since January 22 this year, Australia has performed over two million tests, with an average of 0.4% 
tests returning positive <a href="https://www.health.gov.au/news/health-alerts/novel-coronavirus-2019-ncov-health-alert/coronavirus-covid-19-current-situation-and-case-numbers">[5]</a>. The incidence (number of new cases in a population) of COVID19 in Australia since May is 0.04-0.58 cases per 100000, and the prevalence is less than 0.1%.
This makes pooled testing perfect for the Australian scenario.</p>

<p>There are three common pooled testing methods: Simple grouping (S method), Square Array
grouping (SA method), and Household-based Square Array (HSA method).</p>

<p>In the S method <a href="https://healthpolicy.usc.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/USC_Schaeffer_PooledTesting_WhitePaper_FINAL-1.pdf">[6]</a>, individual samples are combined together and a single test is run on the
grouped sample. If the grouped sample tests positive, then each sample is individually tested.
For our population of 25 million, if the group size is 10, and the prevalence of infected cases in
the population is one percent, then 2,750,000 tests per week are needed. Though this number
is a great deal less than 25 million, it is still beyond Australia’s testing capacity.</p>

<p>In the SA method, a grouped sample (with 10 individuals) is further combined with other groups,
making the group size 100. Individual samples are arranged in a square array of 10 by 10. A
test is run on combined samples of each column group and each row group. As there are 10
columns and 10 rows, 20 tests are run. An individual sample is considered positive if its column
group test or its row group test is positive. For the Australian population, again, we need
5,000,000 tests per week. The difference with the SA method is that each sample is tested twice,
and this decreases the probability of a false negative.</p>

<p>The HSA method <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1joxMjHdWWo9XLFqfTdNXPQRAfeMjHYEyvVljqNCaKyE/edit">[7]</a> is similar to the SA method, except that each sample is a pooled sample of
an entire household. A household sample is considered positive if both its column group and its
row group test is positive. In this case, if a sample is tested positive then a whole household needs
to be quarantined as the test does not differentiate between members of a household. However,
as it is quite likely that all members of the household are infected, under current guidelines the
entire household would most likely be quarantined regardless. This method reduces the required
number of tests to 2,000,000 per week, assuming a household size of 2.5 people.</p>

<p>With each of these three testing methods, the group sizes can be increased to any number to
accommodate any population size and any budget. One criticism is that the number of false
negatives may be too high, but given that the tests are repeated every week, even if some
infected individuals are not detected in one week, they will most likely be detected in the
following week. Thus, pooled testing makes testing of a whole population a feasible goal.
Pooled testing is a method that could enable Australia to test its entire population for COVID19 every week, eliminating the threat of asymptomatic spread and super-spreaders, and
allowing “targeted” quarantine. With the adoption of testing methods like saliva testing
(currently not available in Australia), pooled testing allows the rapid lifting of restrictions while
avoiding a second wave of infection.</p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Saman Eskandarzadeh</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Note: A thought piece also featured in Thinking Outside the Box Thought Pieces Series 2020. The ideas and suggestions in this thought piece received good media attention and interest (e.g., ABC News, newsGP)]]></summary></entry></feed>